in decentralize collective intelligence
what ends up happening is there's a
signal-to-noise dynamic as things move
through notes so if you receive
something from a note from from me for
example I'm telling you this is actually
here we are I'm telling you something
I'm telling you something if you listen
to what I'm saying and in yourself are
able to find that part of what I am
saying that feels true feels right does
not kick off emotions of no greed or
fight or flight or lust or atoms but
feels there's a quality to it you've
just you've built that quality with your
level of capacity where you're like I
don't understand exactly what is being
said here and most of it seems like it's
kind of weird or noisier cringe-worthy
but there's a thread here that feels
very strong I'm gonna separate that up
and now I'm going to skillfully express
it back out when you actually have now
is a positive feedback loop filtering
system if every node is doing that and
by the way those two recursion if every
node is primarily focused initially on
building its discernment and
skillfulness in doing this process all
right then what ends up happening is the
network is amazing and making
sense of subtlety
all right you can take the perception
these subtle broad implicit pattern
recognizers that we're all so gifted
with and grab very vague and weird not
quite knowing what's going on thing put
it into the system and after a couple of
turns it's actually reified to a very
crisp clarity that can be shared so
that's what we're doing because we're
trying to accomplish it's that process
and you notice how much of a burden is
placed on the individual now it's not
like the broadcast modality where most
of your agency is limited to a very
narrow band and you're really relying on
the causal structure that you're
embedded in to do almost all the work in
the decentralized collective
intelligence for to actually work almost
all of the agency is actually on the
you have to have really really effective
responsible individuals and by
responsible I mean is they're they're
able to respond to the environment in
the way that I'm talking about they're
not reacting they're not shifting to a
causal domain they're not saying what
they're supposed to say or rejecting
because they're supposed to reject
they're listening and refining and doing
the work of collaboration think about
collaboration how collaboration works
you and I are collaborating on a song if
we're partners we're really
collaborating I'm gonna be like ah man I
just had this crazy sense and I'd like
to play a terrible sound but you're
listening very closely right and you're
good at it you're good at listening very
closely and you're like you know what is
it like this and you play it back and
what you play back is actually closer to
what I'm feeling ah yes more like that
more like that and then like okay and
then this but now I'm actually a bit
better I because it's more clearing me
because what you did was you refine it
and expressed it back to me with it I
couldn't perceive myself but once I saw
it pop that's insight you just gave me
an insight collaboratively collaborative
insight so now I take a night out put
something back to you and now you're
like oh yeah I totally get it and then
you drop into it and now we're now a
collective intelligence coherence is now
happening in the flu and collaboration
between us and the things that can be
produced are vastly more than what
either one of us could have done
separately now of course this requires
that you have developed a certain level
of discernment I've developed a sort of
discernment we're in a relationship that
allows us to actually use that and we
can talk about that means what the
requirements are and then we've also
built a certain level of skillfulness
and expression so that I'm not creating
noise and expressing it I'm actually
making it more signal when I express it
more real more true I'm increasing the
truth of the expression of the quality
so it's a pretty like I think pretty
concrete example that many people might
be able to grasp and the idea is that
that's what we're doing we're trying to
figure out how to become real
collaborators at scale and well we're
getting better at it we're actually
learning it like we're noticing for
example that our most natural humaneness
has a lot of capability to
separate from non
authenticity from artifice and
authenticity can at least feel true I
mean I feel good artifice can do a
really good job of feeling good but art
but authenticity can feel true even when
it's kind of a clusterfuck I even was
not done exquisitely particularly it's
hard if it feels really true and
authentic there's something in there
that your basic like deep humanist is
like all right I can work with that
where do we go from here and by the way
I'm interested and by the with this
openness hey you know we're just
figuring this out I'm trying what do you
got and you send it back to me
it's symmetrically because we're
available and I listen and I hear you
then we've actually created a
relationship that has that feeling of
trust in the relationship
everything creates an open channel to do
more of it now of course we're late
we're a limited we're limited by
discernment so we're always going to
have to be doing work on improving the
quality of our discernment in all the
modalities that happen to be happening
and we are really limited by our
capacity to express we have to get
better and better being able to express
with clarity with elegance and with I
wanna say it's fidelity meaning we don't
want to put stuff in it that doesn't
belong in it I want to say something
that is also subtly manipulative just
gotta tell the truth pure truth to the
degree in which I can I'm gonna it
up but at least I'm not it up
with stuff that doesn't need to be there
at all so I'm just expressing it and
what happens about that is very good
news because it's extremely powerful
process and the process of collaboration
that's available now because we're all
connected to each other is unprecedented
and that has the capacity to solve all
the problems for dealing with that kind
of a decentralized collective
intelligence with high discerning
individuals with clearly expressing
individuals who are non ego eclis
meaning they are not adding subtly or
intentionally their own into the
signal but are actually simply
endeavoring to share what is
authentically perceived by them to
actually feel true back out with quality
is incomprehensible
capable of making sense and by the way
making choices and doing things so much
so that it's sort of absurd that we just
don't go there you know you want flying
cars and going to the stars this will
get you there it'll solve everything the
amount of bandwidth is available inside
that domain is enormous the problem of
course is that it's hard at an
individual level and it's
counter-current and we've been trained
for generations to do the exact opposite
we've been training for many many many
many generations to insert egoic content
in between everything that we do
we've been changed for several
generations to be simulating thinking
not thinking and so that will to relearn
all that stuff and we have to be doing
it here first each individual has to be
able to take the responsibility and then
learn to trust their own discernment in
relationship you know if I'm in
relationship with you and you are in
fact trying to manipulate me I have to
be in this really weird widely
vulnerable state of actually listening
but then noticing in myself that is a
feeling this little off and then being
able to respond to that as well ideally
to call it out I do this is a way for me
to exquisitely invite you into a higher
level of integrity in yourself in
relationship but also perhaps sometimes
just to be able to be able to make it
safe for myself and for others that's it
like that's the practice as far as I'm
concerned that is the thing that
moreless everybody should be doing right
now full-time and everybody who's good
at it
should be doing it more like it should
show up like if you're if you are good
at it other people should be noticing
that you're good at it and one of the
things that they should be doing is
notice sharing that fact so that the
collective intelligence begins the
process of being able to point its
attention away from say simulation and
artifice and towards truth and towards
capacity building and growth as opposed
to exploitation and plunder and by
definition if you're attending to people
who are helping you build capacity
you're building capacity
so these people are gonna do better so
it's actually good choice for everyone
it is a better choice for everyone to be
endeavoring to play this new game and
the more people who are playing it
better the more obvious that is because
the more actual visceral capacity is
showing up over here and there's a rate
equation that's exponential by the way
that once it starts to hit it is
stretched to achieve criticality escape
velocity and just blows past this old
structure very rapidly no so there we
are
I mean that metaphor of a four-year-old
where this is if you want to play
basketball you have an opportunity to
draft LeBron James he's four it'll take
a while before he's able to actually
take you to the NBA championship but the
opportunity exists to have him on your
team right now by the way and Michael
Jordan they're all there they're just on
the playground therefore they're not
that good right now but in a little
while they're gonna be amazing and maybe
even at 12 like if you imagine five of
the greatest NBA players of all time
playing as twelve-year-old might
actually be a pretty freakin good team
just kind of that's it
[Music]